A Guide to the Clinton Hatcher Camp, Sons of Confederate Veterans Collection, 1896-2006
Thomas Balch Library
Thomas Balch Library
Clinton Hatcher Camp, Sons of Confederate Veterans Collection 1896-2006
Thomas Balch Library
M 025
.33 cu. ft.
Records of Clinton Hatcher Camp, Sons of Confederate Veterans, with a few items from Clinton Hatcher Camp, United Confederate Veterans and United Daughters of the Confederacy, Chapter #29.
Clinton Hatcher Camp, Sons of Confederate Veterans
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Provenance
Bruce McIntosh II, Waterford, VA and unknown
Alternative Form Available
None
Accruals
2000.0008, 2004.0104X, 2005.0103, 1992.0005, 2011.0223X
Historical Information
Clinton Hatcher Camp, Sons of Confederate Veterans, was founded in 1896 in Loudoun County. It was attached to Clinton Hatcher Camp #8, Confederate Veterans, organized in 1888. Confederate Veterans (later United Confederate Veterans Association) was founded to provide aid to indigent Civil War soldiers and their families, and to serve as a memorial organization. United Confederate Veterans was formally organized in June of1889 at a meeting in New Orleans. Its organization was based on a military hierarchy, from a commander-in-chief down to local camps. At its height, United Confederate Veterans' membership was nearly 160,000, about 25 percent of surviving southern soldiers. The last reunion was held in 1951.
By 1896 sons of veterans were expressing interest in forming an organization to preserve and promote southern history. United Confederate Veterans members urged them to do so, noting that the number of surviving veterans was steadily declining. With this encouragement, they met in Richmond to found United Sons of Confederate Veterans, and 1 July 1896 adopted a constitution. The organization's primary goals were to preserve and promote southern history and memorialize southern soldiers. It was organized into three "Armies," states grouped together regionally. Individual states, called divisions, were divided into brigades, and the brigades into camps. Like the United Confederate Veterans, Sons of Confederate Veterans' camps were named for Confederate soldiers.
Following the end of the Civil War, women's organizations formed throughout the south to provide aid to veterans, maintain cemeteries and create monuments. One of the earliest was the Ladies' Auxiliary of the Confederate Soldiers Home in Tennessee, founded in 1890. In 1892 the name was changed to Daughters of the Confederacy, and as time passed it became the custom to call all women's Confederate organizations by this name. By 1894 it was decided that it would benefit the separate groups to come together as one organization. First called National Daughters of the Confederacy, the name was changed to United Daughters of the Confederacy in 1895. The organization was incorporated in 1919.
Sgt. Thomas Clinton Lovett Hatcher, whose name was used by both the Loudoun County United Confederate Veterans and Sons of Confederate Veterans for their camps, was the flag-bearer for the 8th Virginia Infantry. He was the son of Jonah (1810-1887) and Adeline Gregg (1811-1886) Hatcher of Loudoun County. Born 20 December 1839, he was killed in the Battle of Ball's Bluff on 21 October 1861. Ball's Bluff National Cemetery was established in 1865, and a commemorative marker to Hatcher stands outside of the wall surrounding the cemetery.
Scope and Content
The collection is comprised of the records of Clinton Hatcher Camp, Sons of Confederate Veterans, with a few items from Clinton Hatcher Camp, United Confederate Veterans and United Daughters of the Confederacy, Chapter #29. Inclusive dates for the collection are 1888-2006, with most items dating from 1896-1939.
The Sons of Confederate Veterans material includes correspondence, membership application forms, rolls of officers and members, minutes, financial records, and resolutions. There is also a collection of documents with information about Loudoun County Civil War veterans and their descendants. Materials from the ceremony held 28 October 2006 to commemorate the 145th anniversary of the death of Clinton Hatcher include photographs and memorial ribbons. Of additional interest is the Hatcher family Bible, 1811-1887.
A minute book and two publications from United Confederate Veterans are in the collection, along with several receipts and affidavits from United Daughters of the Confederacy. It is unclear how these items came to be included in the Sons of Confederate Veteran's records.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Bibliography
Clinton Hatcher Camp, Sons of Confederate Veterans Collection (M 025), Thomas Balch Library, Leesburg, VA.
Howard, William F. The Battle of Ball's Bluff: "The Leesburg Affair" October 21, 1861. Lynchburg, VA: H.E. Howard, Inc., 1994.
Morgan, James A. III. A Little Short of Boats: The Fight at Ball's Bluff and Edwards Ferry October 21-22, 1861. Ft. Mitchell, KY:Ironclad Publishing, Inc., 2004. [VREF 973.731 MOR]
Poppenheim, Mary B. The History of the United Daughters of the Confederacy. Richmond, VA:Garrett & Massey, Inc., 1938. [VREF 369.1 POP]
Sons of Confederate Veterans. Sons of Confederate Veterans, 1896: Our First Hundred Years. Paducah, Ky: Turner Publishing, 1997. [VREF 973.742 SON]
Sons of Confederate Veterans, http:/www.scv.org/whatis.php.
United Confederate Veterans Association Board, http://www.lib.lsu.edu/special/findaid/u1357.html
Other Finding Aid
None
Contents List
- (Box 1)
  - Minute Book - Clinton Hatcher Camp, Confederate Veterans, 1888-1927
  - By-Laws, Rules of Order and List of Officers of Clinton Hatcher Camp, Confederate Veterans, 12 Mar 1888
  - Abraham Lincoln: An Address Delivered Before R.E. Lee Camp, No. 1, Confederate Veterans, 29 Oct 1909
  - Constitution, By-Laws and Rules of Order, n.d.
  - Minutes, 1927, 1934-1938, n.d.
  - Financial Records, 1923-1939, n.d.
  - Resolutions of Respect and eulogies, 1909-1936, n.d.
  - Correspondence, 1896-1945
  - Applications for membership, 1896, n.d.
  - Application forms (blank), n.d.
  - Rolls of officers and members, 1930-1941, n.d.
  - Veterans and descendents, n.d.
  - Credential Card (blank), n.d.
  - Flyer - Forty-Second Annual Confederate Reunion, June 21-24, 1932
  - Advertisement - Between the Big Parades, by Franklin Wilmer Ward, Aug 1932
  - Receipts - United Daughters of the Confederacy, Chapter #29, 1941-1947
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1898, 2007
  - Charter, 11 March 1981
  - Roster, 1 October 1985
  - Histories, 1986, n.d.
  - State Directory, Virginia Division, Sons of Confederate Veterans, 1986
  - Program - 145th Anniversary of death of Clinton Hatcher, 28 October 2006
  - Ribbons - 145th Anniversary of death of Clinton Hatcher, 28 October 2006
  - Photographs - 145th Anniversary of death of Clinton Hatcher, 28 October 2006
- (BV 001)
  - Hatcher family Bible, 1811-1887